ANIMA JEMATIA KIGEN SIRMA

E-mail: asirma@kilimo.go.ke; janimsy@gmail.com

Mobile: +254 725 788 461

**PROFILE** 

I am a veterinary public health specialist with a passion for promotion of human health through

control of zoonotic diseases and enhancement of food safety of animal derived products for the

improvement of livelihoods of the most vulnerable communities through the livestock value chain.

I have experience and knowledge gained working with the food animal industry and in veterinary

regulation. Working with State Department of Livestock and international research organization

has equipped me with skills that include but not limited to design and implementation of programs

that monitor and protect the state's animal industry, risk assessment, writing of disease manuals

and protocols, capacity building through training and dissemination of knowledge. In addition, I

offer excellent organization skills, ability to motivate and encourage others, a team player but

capable of using own initiative, excellent communicator with all types of individuals on different

levels and able to adapt to any given environment.

WORK EXPERIENCE

August 2019 to present: Chief Veterinary Officer, Veterinary Public Health Section at the State

Department of Livestock, Directorate of Veterinary services, Ministry of Agriculture, Livestock,

Fisheries and Irrigation.

Responsibilities:

• Hygiene inspection

• Inspection and licensing of slaughterhouses and milk processing plants

• Inspection and licensing of meat carriers and containers

Certification for local consumption and exports including online certification for milk and

milk products

• Provision of food quality assurance through enforcement of food laws

1

**July 2018 to July 2019:** Senior Veterinary Officer, Veterinary Public Health Section at the State Department of Livestock, Directorate of Veterinary services, Ministry of Agriculture, Livestock, Fisheries and Irrigation.

## Responsibilities:

- Hygiene inspection
- Inspection and licensing of slaughterhouses and milk processing plants
- Inspection and licensing of meat carriers and containers
- Certification for local consumption and exports
- Provision of food quality assurance through enforcement of food laws

**December 2015 to June 2018:** Senior Veterinary Officer, Personal Assistant to the Director of Veterinary Services (DVS), Directorate of Veterinary services, Ministry of Agriculture, Livestock, Fisheries and Irrigation.

### Responsibilities:

- Maintaining the technical diary of the DVS including planning local field visits and drafting back to office reports;
- Handling delegated correspondences and e-mails
- Assisting in preparation of technical presentations for local, domestic and international conferences and symposia'
- Coordinating response to questionnaires from external partners;
- Committee member of various committees formed by DVS (Key Results Areas Team, Casuals Engagement Committee, Administration block refurbishment committee);

**November 2014 to November 2015:** Senior Veterinary Officer, Veterinary Epidemiology and Economics Section at the State Department of Livestock, Directorate of Veterinary services, Ministry of Agriculture, Livestock, Fisheries and Irrigation.

## Responsibilities:

- Passive and active disease surveillance
- Assisting in design and implementation of socio-economic impact assessment of animal diseases on food security and livelihoods.
- Carrying disease outbreak investigations
- Conducting risk analysis on animal and zoonotic diseases nationally, regionally and internationally

- Analysis of data, disease mapping, zonation of diseases and livestock movement mapping
- Preparing reports and giving feedback to national (including counties, districts and regions), regional and international organizations

March 2011 to October 2014: Veterinary Officer 1, Veterinary Epidemiology and Economics Unit at the State Department of Livestock, Directorate of Veterinary services, Ministry of Agriculture, Livestock, Fisheries and Irrigation.

October 2014 to December 2014: worked as a part-time Public Health lecturer at College of Agriculture and Veterinary Sciences, University of Nairobi.

Units taught: 1) Risk analysis 2) Food laws and standards

**August 2012 to Present (Part time):** PhD fellow at International Livestock Research Institute (ILRI). Project: Risk and Economic Assessment of Mycotoxins in the Kenyan Dairy-Feed Value Chain.

### Study objectives:

- To estimate aflatoxin contamination rates and consumption along the Kenyan dairy value chain
- To determine risk factors associated with aflatoxins along the dairy value chain in Kenya
- To conduct risk assessment of aflatoxins in the dairy value chain in Kenya
- To identify best option to reduce risk to human health by aflatoxins in the dairy value chain in Kenya.

May 2012 to July 2012: Research assistant, FoodAfrica baseline survey {Meru and Makueni baseline study} under the project Measuring and Mitigating the risk of Aflatoxins in poor milk consumers and maize producers.

# Responsibilities:

- Household survey using structured questionnaires
- Design of data entry templates/database
- Decoding of Focus Group Discussions
- Data entry, cleaning and coding
- Data analysis

#### **EDUCATION**

**2013 to Present:** Doctor of Philosophy in Veterinary Public Health, University of Nairobi. Working on research thesis titled: Risk assessment of aflatoxins in the Kenyan dairy value chain.

2009 to 2012: Master of Science in Veterinary Public Health (MVPH), University of Nairobi.

Thesis title: Evaluation of human exposure to aflatoxins in Nandi North, South and Central districts.

**2004 to 2009**: Bachelor of Veterinary Medicine (BVM), College of Agriculture and Veterinary Sciences, University of Nairobi.

**1999 to 2002:** Kenya Certificate of Secondary Education (KCSE), Kipsigis Girls' High School, Kericho.

#### SHORT TRAINING/WORKSHOPS

- Microbial Food Quality and Safety Course by DFC Scholarship Programme/Danish Ministry of Foreign Affairs held at Copenhagen, Denmark, 3<sup>rd</sup> to 28<sup>th</sup> June 2019
- 2017 Foreign Agricultural Service Cochran Fellowship Program on agricultural extension and farmers leadership held at Alabama, USA 18<sup>th</sup> to 29<sup>th</sup> September, 2017
- Regional training on data analysis, risk analysis and risk mapping for transboundary animal diseases by AU-IBAR and IGAD/ICPALD Entebbe, Uganda from 12<sup>th</sup> to 16<sup>th</sup> December, 2016
- Senior Management Course by Kenya School of Government 4<sup>th</sup> to 19<sup>th</sup> July, 2016

## **PUBLICATIONS**

- 1) **Sirma AJ**, Makita K., Grace D., Senerwa D. and Lindahl J (2019). Aflatoxin exposure from milk in rural Kenya and the contribution to the risk of liver cancer. Toxins (Basel). Vol. 11.
- 2) **Sirma AJ**, Lindahl JF, Makita K, Senerwa D, Mtimet N, Kang'ethe EK and Grace D (2018). The impacts of aflatoxin standards on health and nutrition in sub-Saharan Africa: The case of Kenya. Global Food Security Vol. 18 (57–61).

- 3) **Sirma AJ**, Senerwa DM, Lindahl JF, Makita K, Mtimet N, Kang'ethe EK and Grace D (2016). Aflatoxin B1 occurrence in millet, sorghum and maize from four agro-ecological zones in Kenya. African J. Food, Agric. Nutr. Vol 16 (3)
- 4) Senerwa DM, **Sirma AJ**, Mtimet N, Kang'ethe EK, Grace D and Lindahl JF (2016). Prevalence of aflatoxin in feeds and cow milk from five counties in Kenya. African J. Food, Agric. Nutr. Vol 16 (3)
- 5) Kiama TN, **Sirma AJ**, Senerwa DM, Waithanji EM, Lindahl JF, Ochungo P, Poole J, Kang'ethe EK, and Grace D (2016). A Qualitative Assessment of Dietary Exposure to Mycotoxins within the Kenya Dairy Value Chain and the Role of Gender. African J. Food, Agric. Nutr. Vol 16 (3)
- 6) **Sirma AJ**, Ouko EO, Murithi G, Mburugu C, Mapenay I, Ombui JN, Kang'ethe EK and Korhonen H (2015). Prevalence of aflatoxin contamination in cereals from Nandi county, Kenya. Int. J. Agric.Sc & Vet.Med Vol. 3, No. 3.

### **CONFERENCE PROCEEDINGS**

- Systematic Review of Mycotoxins with a One Health Perspective. Ecohealth conference held at Grand Bassam, Cote d'Ivoire; 1<sup>st</sup> – 5<sup>th</sup> October 2013
- 2) Aflatoxin M1 survey in rural households in four agro-ecological zones in Kenya. FoodAfrica midterm seminar at University of Helsinki, Finland; 16<sup>th</sup> June, 2014

# PROFESSIONAL MEMBERSHIPS & AFFILIATIONS

Kenya Veterinary Board (KVB no. 2335)

Kenya Veterinary Association (KVA no. 0623)

#### REFEREES

1. Dr. Delia Grace Randolph 2. Dr. Joyce Thaiya

Program Leader Deputy Director of Veterinary Services

Food Safety and Zoonoses, Integrated Ministry of Agriculture, Livestock and

Sciences Fisheries

International Livestock Research Institute Directorate of Veterinary Services,

P.O Box 30709-00100, Nairobi, Kenya

Email: D.Randolph@cgiar.org

Mobile number: +254 733 280 188

Private Bag 00625, Kangemi, Nairobi, Kenya

Email: thaiyajcw@yahoo.com

Mobile number: +254 722 952346

3. Prof. Jackson N Ombui

Dept. Public Health Pharmacology and

Toxicology

College of Agriculture and Veterinary

Sciences,

University of Nairobi.

P.O. Box 29053, Nairobi, Kenya.

Email: jombui@uonbi.ac.ke

Mobile number: +254 724 354 865